Today is a very important day for all of us Sahaja Yogis,
امروز روز بسیار مهمی برای همه ما ساهاجایوگی‌هاست،
because today Shri Ganesha was born.
چون امروز شری گانشا متولد شد.
Shri Ganesha is whom we worship
شری گانشا کسی است که ما او را ستایش می‌کنیم
and because of whom we got our awakening (jagruti).
و به خاطر اوست که شما خودآگاهی خود را گرفتید.
However much you may remember Him,
فرقی نمی‌کند که چقدر شما به او فکر کنید،
until you do not know His special qualities, you cannot attain Him.
تا وقتی ویژگی‌های خاص او را ندانید، نمی‌توانید به او برسید.
His special quality is that He is the embodiment of purity (shuddha swaroop)
ویژگی خاص او این است که او مظهر پاکی است؛ (شودْها سواروُپ)
and complete Master of the Universe.
و استاد تمام عیار عالم است.
He is the incarnation of the Supreme, of Brahman.
او اینکارنیشن خداوند متعال، براهما است.
By coming into this world He has created music (sangeet), rhythm (taal) and notes (sur).
با آمدن به این دنیا، او موسیقی (سنگیت)، ریتم (تآل) و نُت‌ها (سور) را آفریده است.
By His Grace only people become one with music (talleen).
فقط با رحمت اوست که مردم با موسیقی (تالین) یگانه می‌شوند.
A small boy who came into the world and did such great work!
یک پسر کوچک به دنیا آمد و چنین کار بزرگی کرد!
He has given so many things to everyone and even today He is active.
او چیزهای زیادی را به همه عطا کرده است و حتی امروز هم او فعال است.
Shri Ganesha’s Puja, no matter how much you do it, it is not enough.
مهم نیست که چقدر پوجای شری ‌گانشا را انجام می‌دهید، این کافی نیست.
A lot of people say we don’t see Shri Ganesha, even after worshiping Him so much, we do not attain Him.
کسان زیادی می‌گویند "ما شری‌گانشا را نمی‌بینیم، حتی پس از ستایش بسیار او، به او دست نمی‌یابیم."
He is omnipotent, omnipresent and in everything,
او قادر مطلق است و در همه جا و در همه چیز حاضر است
but you cannot recognize Him until you are Realized.
ولی تا وقتی خودآگاه نباشید، نمی‌توانید او را بشناسید.
After your realization you can recognize what Shri Ganesha is.
بعد از خودآگاهی است که می‌توانید بفهمید شری گانشا چیست.
Shri Ganesha is Purity, the Pure Spirit.
شری گانشا پاکی است، روح پاک.
When He is awakened within us, then we have no questions left.
وقتی او درون ما بیدار شود، هیچ سوالی برای ما باقی نمی‌ماند.
Then we are successful, in whichever task we undertake.
بعد در هر کاری که انجام بدهیم موفق می‌شویم.
We find joy in everything we do.
و ما مسرت را در هر کاری که انجام می‌دهیم می‌بینیم.
He is the embodiment of joy and gives joy to everyone.
او مظهر مسرت است و به همه مسرت می‌بخشد.
To serve Him is the ultimate dharma (paramdharma).
خدمت کردن به او نهایت دْهارما (پارادْهارما) است.
To serve Him means to look after small children, to serve them,
خدمت به او یعنی چه؟ مراقبت از بچه‌های کوچک، خدمت کردن به آنها،
to protect them, to make sure there is no cruelty towards them.
حفاظت از آنها، کسب اطمینان از این که هیچ خشونتی به آن‌ها روا نمی‌شود.
This pleases Him very much.
این کار او را بسیار خرسند می‌کند.
Such an embodiment of love, such a simple-hearted Shri Ganesha, was born today.
یک چنین مظهر عشقی، چنین شری گانشای پاکدلی امروز متولد شد.
This is the importance of this day.
اهمیت این روز همین است.
Today, if you ask for any wish, then Shri Ganesha will fulfill it.
امروز هر آرزویی بکنید، شری گانشا آن را برآورده خواهد کرد.
It is His right to fulfill all your desires, because you are all realized.
این حق اوست که تمام آرزوهای شما را برآورده کند، چون همه شما خودآگاه هستید.
Ask Him from all your heart, and He will help you in every way, every moment, and every instant.
با تمام وجود از او بخواهید و او از هر جهت، در هر لحظه و در هر آن به شما کمک می‌کند.
Today is a very big day,
امروز روز بسیار بزرگی است،
because verily the pure Spirit itself has taken birth today.
چون روح پاک واقعی امروز تولد یافته است.
And He already had such a spiritual, eternal state
و او از قبل چنین مرتبه معنوی و ابدی را داشته است
that many people could not comprehend it or write about it.
که بسیاری از مردم نمی‌توانستند آن را درک کنند یا در مورد آن بنویسند.
Many people didn’t tell anything; they wrote only what they could understand.
خیلی از مردم چیزی نمی‌گفتند، آنها فقط هر چه را می‌توانستند درک کنند می‌نوشتند.
But you can understand that just by Shri Ganesha’s name you get your realization.
ولی شما می‌توانید درک کنید که فقط با نام شری گانشا می‌توانید خودآگاهی خودتان را بگیرید.
Just by taking His name, any disease or any pain will disappear.
فقط با بردن نام او، هر بیماری یا هر دردی از بین خواهد رفت.
He is eternal.
او جاودانه است.
He is always present within us.
او همیشه درون ما حاضر است.
When you get your realization, you can feel His presence.
وقتی شما خودآگاهی‌تان را بگیرید، می‌توانید حضور او را احساس کنید.
And if you are not realized, you cannot understand.
و اگر خودآگاه نباشید، نمی‌توانید درک کنید.
That is why people get misled and do wrong things.
برای همین است که مردم گمراه می‌شوند و کارهای اشتباه انجام می‌دهند.
But with Shri Ganesha’s blessings, you can do so many things,
ولی با رحمت شری گانشا، شما می‌توانید کارهای بسیاری را انجام دهید
and you won’t feel greedy nor have any problems,
و نه حس طمع خواهید داشت و نه هیچ مشکلی،
because He does all the work for you. He takes care of you.
چون او تمام کارها را برای شما انجام می‌دهد. او از شما مراقبت می کند.
Though He is a little boy, He looks after you.
با آن‌که پسری کوچک است، از شما مراقبت می‌کند.
It’s a tremendous power.
این قدرتی فوق العاده است.
By Shri Ganesha’s power, several works are manifested.
با قدرت شری گانشا، کارهای متعددی نمایان می‌شوند.
For Me, He is the purest ever and My own.
برای من، او پاک‌ترین و از آنِ من است
I trouble Him a lot.
من او را خیلی به زحمت می‌اندازم.
When somebody tries to trouble Me,
وقتی کسی می‌خواهد مرا به دردسر بیندازد،
I ask Him to handle this fellow and to make him alright.
از او می‌خواهم که این شخص را اداره و او را خوب کند.
When this fellow is not manageable by Me, when there is a difficult person
وقتی این شخص توسط من قابل مدیریت نباشد، وقتی فردی بدقلق باشد
and it is not possible for Me to handle him, then He does the job.
و امکان اداره کردن  او را نداشته باشم، او کار را انجام می دهد.
So today is very auspicious, as He was born this day.
پس امروز، روزی بسیار فرخنده است، چرا که او امروز متولد شد.
Secondly, today is Panchami (the fifth day).
ثانیا امروز پانچامی (روز پنجم) است.
This Panchami is recognized because on this day we wear special clothes.
پانچامی را به این می‌شناسند که در این روز ما لباس‌های خاصی می‌پوشیم.
Whatever we wear is so that our body is properly covered.
هر چه می‌پوشیم باید به گونه‌ای باشد که تمام بدن ما خوب پوشانده شود.
The sense of chastity that our body has is because of Him;
حس پاکدامنی که بدن ما دارد به خاطر اوست؛
Lajja Rupena Samsthita [the one who resides in the form of bashful modesty].
"لاجّا روپِنا سامستیتا" (کسی که مظهر حجب و حیا و فروتنی است.)
So if you have any sense of chastity, it is because of Him.
پس اگر هر احساسی از حیا و پاکدامنی دارید، به خاطر او است.
That will benefit you immensely.
این احساس بی‌نهایت به خیر و صلاح شما خواهد بود.
You cannot feel joyous until you worship Shri Ganesha.
تا زمانی که شری گانشا را ستایش نکنید، نمی توانید احساس شادی کنید.
By worshipping Shri Ganesha, your joy increases.
با ستایش شری گانشا، شادی شما بیشتر می شود.
You become joyous, because He is the personification of joy [anand swaroop].
شما شاد و مسرور می‌شوید، چرا که او مظهر شادی است؛ (آناندا سواروپا)
Because of this, we have both things today: His birthday and His help.
به همین دلیل، ما امروز هر دو چیز را داریم: تولد او و کمک او.
We seek His help in any work we do. Such is our way.
ما در هر کاری که انجام می‌دهیم از او کمک می خواهیم. این روش ماست.
But we don’t see what we do to establish Him. Our attention does not go in that direction.
اما نگاه نمی‌کنیم که برای تثبیت او چه کاری باید انجام دهیم. توجه ما به آن سمت نمی‌رود
That we should also do something, that we should also develop our state,
این که ما نیز باید کاری انجام دهیم، این که ما نیز باید وضع خود را بهتر کنیم،
that we should have a state in which Shri Ganesha is awakened within us,
شری گانشا درون ما بیدار شود، که از این طریق هرگز در مسیر اشتباه قرار نگیریم.
Those who are rooted in Ganesha are special.
کسانی که ریشه در شری‌گانشا دارند خاص هستند.
They despise all the wrong things in this world, and they do not do anything wrong,
آنها تمام چیزهای اشتباه در این جهان را خوار می‌شمارند و هیچ کار اشتباهی انجام نمی‌دهند،
because Shri Ganesha stops them.
چرا که شری‌گانشا آن‌ها را متوقف می‌کند.
They cannot enjoy wrong activities.
آنها از هیچ کار خطایی لذت نمی‌برند.
This is Shri Ganesha’s great blessing, that you have entered a new, joyous life.
این رحمت بزرگ شری‌گانشا است که شما وارد چنین زندگی جدید و شادی شده‌اید.
So today in His service, in order to make him joyous,
پس امروزدر خدمتش، برای آنکه او را مسرور کنید،
sing His praise and glory, so that He may be pleased.
آواز حمد و ثنای او را سر دهید، باشد که او خرسند گردد.
My eternal blessings to all of you.
رحمت‌های جاودانه من بر همه شما.